Shane Adam Young | Software Engineer

Software engineer with over 9 years of experience in finance and banking, with the ability to bridge both technical and professional leadership skills. A self starter that is motivated to find new ways to positively impact and evolve the world with the use of technology. Having a growth mindset fuels my desire to continuously learn and create high-quality products & solutions. With a strong business acumen, clear and effective communication skills, and prior experience in a collaborative team environment, I bring a unique and invaluable perspective as a developer.

Technical Skills

Languages - JavaScript, HTML5, CSS, Python, SQL | Libraries and Frameworks - React, Express, Node, Django, Bootstrap Relational Database - PostgreSQL | NoSQL Database - MongoDB Other - REST APIs, JSON APIs, AWS S3, CI / CD (GitHub), Git

Professional Experience

Software Engineer | The Opportunity Project 2023 (Volunteer) | Remote

08/2023 - Current

- Collaborate with a cross-functional product development team of 15+ Software Engineers, Data Scientists, Data Analysts, UI / UX Designers, and UX Researchers on The Opportunity Project, led by the US Census Bureau, the US Department of Commerce, and the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau.
- Utilize federal data to build a web application that facilitates a more competitive credit card shopping experience for consumers and ensures that consumers have the ability to find the credit card that best meets their needs.
- Design a front-end application featuring React and Tailwind, focused on financial education for first time credit card owners/users.
- Receive feedback from team members via code reviews and research various design patterns to optimize our target market.

AVP - Portfolio Manager, Commercial Banking | U.S. Bank | Portland, OR

09/2021 - 05/2023

- Managed a dynamic \$65 million portfolio of commercial credit exposure, encompassing term loans, revolving lines of credit, and ACH transactions. Strategically allocated resources to optimize profitability and minimize risk.
- Conducted underwriting for new and existing clients via comprehensive written analyses that evaluates their financial statements and market trends.
- Utilized organization skills to manage multiple transactions in a time-sensitive manner, consistently exceeding expectations by completing transactions within 4-6 weeks.
- Leveraged Salesforce CRM to discover new revenue opportunities that also prioritizes customer success.

Portfolio Manager, Specialized Finance | U.S. Bank | Portland, OR

04/2018 - 09/2021

- Managed a portfolio of 55 customers, overseeing \$150 million in credit exposure across a wide range of industries, including healthcare, government, non-profit, and commercial & industrial sectors.
- Completed comprehensive credit underwriting requests for transactions exceeding \$1 million. Analyzed various credit information to assess credit worthiness and make informed decisions to approve or decline the request.
- Mitigated credit risk by analyzing operating performance, industry trends, and market dynamics. Tailored risk management strategies based on industry-specific risks.

Software Development Projects

<u>Digital Payments App</u> - Python, Django, PostgreSQL, JavaScript

09/2023

A digital payments application, similar to Venmo, CashApp, and Zelle; utilizing back-end services and API frameworks.

- Developed a comprehensive transaction handling system, allowing users to send and receive funds securely.
- Demonstrated competency in Django by creating dynamic views and managing complex data models for seamless application functionality.
- Designed and implemented core banking functionalities, including account management, KYC, and transaction processing.

Oregon Winery Review App - MongoDB, Express, Node, React, JavaScript, CSS, BootStrap

08/2023

A MERN Stack web application for users to write their experience at wineries in the Willamette Valley region of Oregon.

- Implemented full CRUD functionality, enabling users to seamlessly create, read, update, and delete their reviews.
- Designed the application as a Single Page Application (SPA) using React, providing users with a seamless and responsive browsing experience.
- Utilized data seeding techniques to prepopulate the application's MongoDB database with a selection of wineries in Oregon, ensuring an engaging user experience from the outset.

Zero Based Budget App - MongoDB, Express, Node, JavaScript, Embedded JS, Bootstrap, CSS

07/2023

A budgeting application to simplify the process of tracking and managing personal finances.

- Built a full stack CRUD (create, read, update, delete) application in a one week sprint.
- Integrated Google OAuth authentication to streamline user access and enhance the application's security. Enabled users to log in using their Google credentials, ensuring a convenient and trustworthy sign-in process.
- Utilized Bootstrap to design a visually appealing and user-friendly interface.

EDUCATION

General Assembly, Bootcamp | Remote **Software Engineering / Computer Science**

05/2023 - 08/2023

University of Portland | Portland, OR B.B.A - Finance, Pamplin School of Business

08/2010 - 05/2014